Hi. Uh
So, this talk has a strange history.
Uh we were
there were some a group from China asked
me, will I give two special days of
talks
for them on these two days, and I said
yes.
And then they couldn't come.
And uh I think it's bad luck to cancel
something. So, I just decided to do it
anyway.
And uh I thought it's a good chance to
uh start again the the devil debates an
angel.
So,
I was checking this afternoon how much
we finished and how much we have to go.
I started this text 7 years ago.
We are 11% through it.
Uh so, that's we'll finish in uh
two Yeah, 70 years.
Uh
2087.
But, if I have time, I'll try to speed
up, okay?
Um so, let me tell you about this text.
My Lama taught it to me. He started
teaching it, he never finished. And
he did He only had 25 years.
Uh so, uh he he taught us this text. And
it's a very, very beautiful poem. It's a
long poem, and in Tibetan language, it's
called Dung Ten Shang Dep. Say Dung Ten.
Shang Dep.
So, Dung Ten means
uh the tendency to misunderstand the
world.
And Shang Dep means argument
or debate.
And uh in in America or in the West, we
have this custom of the devil and the
angel inside of one person's mind.
Like
if Geshe Michael's deciding whether to
eat his third sweet roll
in the same day, then the devil will
say, "Oh, yeah, that's okay. We can do
yoga tomorrow."
And then the angel says, "Well, maybe
two is enough."
You know, and so all of us during our
lives, we have
times when our own mind is arguing with
our own mind, right?
And we're trying to decide what's the
right thing to do. So,
this is the This is the idea of this
text. To give you a little bit about the
author,
uh his name is uh
Lobsang Chukyi Gyaltsen.
And uh he's
They in Tibet, they say he lived to 100,
but he didn't actually. Uh he lived to
Oh, I don't have it here. Anyway, 92,
something like that.
Um
And he was the first Panchen Lama, okay?
So, in Tibet, there are two great
lineage of of high lama.
And uh the Panchen Lama is is one of
them. He was born in 1662, I think,
something like that.
1557, I don't know.
Uh but he's one of the highest lamas in
Tibet. And the first one, as usual, was
very special.
And he was a great poet.
Uh he's a great philosopher. We study a
lot of his books. Uh three of the 18
advanced courses of ACI are written by
him.
And this is a Lamrim called the Path to
Bliss.
Uh so, he wrote that. So, people who
study
uh Diamond Way, Vajrayana in our
tradition, they they start with those uh
three courses
based on the first Panchen Lama's works.
Uh during those three courses, you Can
you turn the mic down a little bit? It's
I I could hold it like that, but it's
Uh,
and uh,
I put in that uh, Lamrim, I spiced it
with some of his poetry.
He wrote a lot of tantric poetry,
uh, which was very beautiful, and it's
recited in some of the great tantric
colleges in Tibet. So, I translated
that, and I threw some into the course.
And without permission, one of my
students published it. Uh, so if you,
you know, are feeling
like adventurous, um, you can read it.
Uh, it and Jigme can tell you how to get
copies of it, okay?
Uh, and I found it on Amazon. It's on
Amazon, but
it's pretty uh,
out out there.
Uh, so anyway,
I like him especially because of the
story that he was doing retreat
uh, near a certain valley in Tibet.
And uh, his
his attendant came to him and said uh,
"You have to stop the retreat." And he
said, "Why?" And he said, "There's a war
going to break out this evening.
There are two armies headed towards each
other. They're going to meet in the
valley right in front of your cave,
and there's going to be a war, you know?
And uh,
so he said, "Well,
I will take care of that." And he left
retreat, and he walked down, and he
stood between these two armies.
And he yelled at both of them and said,
"You want to have a war, you have to
kill me first."
You know? And nobody wanted to kill him
because he was already famous.
And then he he said, "Let me meet with
the two generals of the two armies." And
and they came, and
and he said uh, "You know, I'm pretty
famous." And they said, "Yeah." And he
said, "We're going to have to kill me if
you want to have this war."
And they said, "Yeah." And then he said,
"Also, I have a lot of gold."
You know, and if you don't fight, I'll
give I'll make each of you rich.
You know, and they said, "That sounds
good."
And uh
so,
he actually uh is credited with stopping
a war by bribing
uh both of the two generals.
So, I just really admire him like that.
It's rare
uh in Buddhism
to have people like that, you know, high
lama who will go out and stand between
two armies and risk his life.
And I really like him for that, okay?
So, I have this plan tonight. Uh
I thought tonight we could review what
what we did before cuz we did start 7
years ago.
And then I stopped about 3 years ago cuz
I was so busy.
And
let's see how it goes. I don't like to
not finish a text. Uh so, if there's
interest
uh
and if my partner says it's okay,
you know, maybe we can do one or two
nights a month or something like that
and try to finish it.
Uh cuz it's very exquisite. My lama
started it.
My lama started it, but he didn't he
didn't finish it. It's It's a difficult
text to teach because there's no
commentary.
And it's colloquial. It's like, "Hey
man, what's up?"
And uh it's colloquial of his
province uh which is even worse. So,
but the ideas are are classical. He's a
classical thinker.
So, we can figure out,
you know, the ideas We can figure out
the language from the ideas, okay? So,
and I'm at an age in my life and a and a
point in my training where I realize
if I don't translate it, nobody else
can.
So, I might as well just try.
And Kamalashila is the same. We're going
to do Kamalashila in about 2 weeks,
right?
And uh no one's taught it for a thousand
years.
Uh
and a lot of it's very difficult, but I
just figured no one else is
going to have uh the the training I had
to uh try
to read it and to
crack it. So, Kamalashila is also a
problem. There are no commentaries
and we are missing the Sanskrit.
And I think the translator was drunk
when he translated it
in into Tibetan.
Uh
so, it's really weird.
Uh and we've been trying to get through
it, you know, and but I just figured no
one else is going to be able to even
try. So,
let's go. Okay. So far, I'm pretty
comfortable with this text, okay.
Uh I'm going to review for you the whole
uh tonight will be a review
and then tomorrow we'll do new stuff.
Unfortunately, it happens every time I
teach this and that's why it's so slow.
Um
So,
the name, the technical name of uh the
whole book is Shilam der desum chakka
chambu lung nun zin der tsam pe shed ap
ten nun zin nyi gyi shang da
which means uh
this is a book
about Mahamudra, okay? Mahamudra.
And uh Mahamudra is a very famous word
in India.
Uh it can refer to many things, okay? Uh
one is a a yoga pose where you
hold this foot up to your ear and you
grab the other toe.
And
uh that's a Mahamudra pose and it's
supposed to open your channels in a very
unique way.
It's like holding your foot to your ear
as if you're making a phone call.
And then holding the other toe straight
and uh
that's called Mahamudra pose. Um
Mahamudra can mean
uh the practice of
deep practice with your consort, with
your man or woman partner. It can refer
to that.
And uh in this case uh Mahamudra
refers to the emptiness of the mind,
okay?
So, and it's a special meditation to
meditate
uh on the emptiness of the mind. So, the
object of meditation in Mahamudra is
your own mind.
Uh we have a version of it in DCI where
we focus on the mind
and we learn to watch the thoughts,
okay? So, normally we are in our
thoughts
and it's difficult for us to observe our
thoughts as an observer. We tend to
think and not to watch ourselves think.
So, in Mahamudra you choose it's a
famous
uh object of meditation
uh because it's moving.
And it its nature is to keep you awake
in the meditation. To watch your own
mind is a fascinating thing
because it's so wild.
You know? So, uh instead of meditating
on a Buddha picture or instead of
meditating on uh
you know, like death or something like
that, you're watching your own mind and
and so, that kind of meditation
where you watch your own mind uh is
called Mahamudra.
Um and you and you just try to see the
emptiness of the mind, okay? And we'll
talk about what that means. It doesn't
mean uh you forgot where your keys are
or something like that.
Okay?
Mm.
Now, I'm just going to go quickly
through the first 135 verses
tonight. Okay, my plan is do we have
refreshments you guys?
We do.
Really? Uh
but okay, if we take a break?
Okay. All right, there's Mexican food.
Uh
Okay, let's just go through these first
few verses. The very first thing he does
and and by the way later I will
Mm
Yeah, okay, we can use that.
I wasn't going to display it but this
okay. We'll we'll go for it. It's okay.
Uh
First thing he does of course is to
honor his own teacher
and to call his teacher the highest of
all secret angels.
Then he describes and I've added these
things in the
bold print just so you can follow where
you are, okay?
And the whole text so far has been
it was supposed to have been sent to
everybody who's registering so you could
read ahead. Uh I don't know if it was
sent and I don't know how many people
read it.
But anyway, uh I added these
headers to make life easier for you so
you can see where he's going, okay?
Uh
so
the Mahamudra or great seal. Mudra means
seal.
And it refers to the seal that a king
uses to stamp things.
Nowadays, the American president
unfortunately has
a red box
and he's followed around by some Air
Force colonel
and inside of that box are all the
nuclear buttons. Uh
and it's chained to the colonel's hand
and it's always within 100 ft of the
president even if he's asleep. There's a
guy there standing there. He can launch
a nuclear attack in
15 minutes. Any Any American president.
I assume it's the same in China. So,
anyway,
uh you need some verification codes. If
the
people
waiting with the missiles get these
codes, they will shoot the missile. If
they don't get the codes, they will
wait.
There's a famous Russian guy who got the
codes by accident
and refused to sh- pull the button.
And he just passed away a few weeks ago.
He's very famous. He's They He's called
the guy who saved the world.
Uh
so, anyway, uh
this is the same in ancient times. If
you got a letter from the emperor
or the king and it had the stamp on it,
then you could attack Mongolia or you
could attack Tibet or, you know, India,
Nepal, if you got a stamp.
So, that's called mudra. That stamp that
a king uses is called a mudra.
And in the case of a spiritual partner,
uh
which is also called a mudra,
uh the explanation is that the king
should never be without their seal.
And no one else should have, you know,
the king should always be close their
seal like the American president's close
to their
nuclear codes, you see?
So, it means that uh your relationship
with your
with your spiritual partner should be
that tight. Uh there should never be uh
you should never be far from your
spiritual partner. So,
that's why traditionally that partner is
called an a mudra, okay?
Uh
so, here he's going to talk about maha
mudra in three stages of life, which we
call shilam debosum. Okay, say she.
She.
Lam.
Debu.
She.
Lam.
Debu.
Be a little more animated, okay?
Uh cuz it's 9:00 and, you know,
I know you just had food, which is a bad
idea, but
Okay, she means uh foundation.
Lam means path.
And deb means result. Uh so, she means
How does
How does the emptiness of the mind
manifest itself in a normal person
without any training? Okay? Do they have
Mahamudra?
Okay? And then lam means
while they're practicing Buddhism daily
uh what is Mahamudra in that person's
mind? And then deb means after they
achieve enlightenment and they become a
Buddha
then how do we describe their Mahamudra?
Okay? So, we we say shi lam deb. There's
three Mahamudras, okay?
Uh and he he explains them.
Right now, if you notice the text, it
sounds like someone just talking, okay?
Someone teaching.
What is Mahamudra in a person as they
normally are?
It's the true nature of their mind,
okay?
And it's come along with mind
since the beginning since no beginning,
okay?
Buddhism says the mind has no beginning
because a moment of the mind cannot be
created except by a a previous moment of
the mind.
The it's a unique stuff. Consciousness
is a unique stuff. We don't believe that
you will ever be able to create a mind
with chemicals.
Uh it mind the primary cause the mind,
which is consciousness, must be a
previous moment of consciousness.
So, we believe therefore that the mind
has no beginning and no end, okay?
So, you have always been here. You have
lived in different bodies and different
countries and different planets, but
but your mind has no beginning and the
emptiness of your mind has no beginning,
okay?
We'll talk more about the emptiness of
your mind. Mm.
Uh because people don't understand the
emptiness of their mind, they have to
live in
pain, okay? Pain, I mean, on its most
basic level
is that all of us have to get old and
die.
It doesn't matter how smart you are, how
strong you are, how powerful you are,
how rich you are.
We are all the same.
Voltaire said, "Fellow suffers for a
day."
You know, we we all have the same
future.
Uh and that
dismal future has been created by the by
your mind, the condition of your mind,
okay?
Uh if you could
understand the nature of your mind, uh
you could change it.
Death would not be inevitable, okay?
Uh
And then he says, uh
"The only way to stop misunderstanding
in the mind is wisdom."
And then he talks about, you know,
everybody
in the world
sees the emptiness of their mind briefly
uh as they die, okay? During the death
process,
after your external senses uh withdraw,
then you have a brief
uh you are briefly in the presence of of
emptiness, but you don't recognize it
for what it is, and you cannot use it
cuz you're not trained. Every person
during the process of death
uh
is in the presence of emptiness and
doesn't recognize it, okay? And that
emptiness during the death process,
which some of you studied already in
great detail,
is called the clear light, okay?
Uh
And he says here, "It goes from people
who are at the highest Bodhisattva level
down to the insects on the all insects
have
They also
are exposed to emptiness as they die,
but they don't realize it. Okay. If they
could recognize it, they could
get freedom, but they can't. Okay.
Then he talks about the first time you
see
you use the emptiness of your mind
directly the first time you see
emptiness directly which is called the
path of seeing. Okay.
A big moment in a person's life.
The next uh
period on the path
is after you see emptiness directly and
you keep using it to perfect your life.
Okay.
And then
uh
when you perfect your life, you become
omniscient. You become a Buddha. Okay.
And then he uses the tantric word for
enlightenment which is the union of
bliss and voidness daytong.
And
you can see emptiness directly and you
can be a
angel at the same time. Okay.
And then then the conversation goes
cuckoo.
Okay. Then the conversation gets
chaotic. Okay. Whoever's talking which
sounds like the first Panchen Lama so
far. Okay. Whoever's talking says, "By
the way." And here's where the trouble
starts for the next 70 years.
Okay. This is where the trouble starts.
He says, "By the way,
uh
that
that Buddha
that you reach is also empty.
Okay. The Buddha you become by mastering
Mahamudra
is also empty. And if you don't think
so, you have a problem.
Okay? So, this Buddha
has
has been born from two conditions, okay?
Number one,
uh while the person was becoming a
Buddha for millions of years, they made
a prayer
that they should become an angel who can
help all beings.
They From their side, they made a
prayer.
And then from the student side,
they were wishing to meet
a Buddha, okay? So, two things join
together. The
the Buddha made a prayer, "When I become
a Buddha, I want to help everybody."
And the student made a prayer,
"I hope I get to meet the Buddha one
day." Okay? And then those two causes
create a Buddha.
If the Buddha had no causes like that,
they wouldn't be empty. Because they
have causes like that, they are empty.
What does empty mean?
They don't exist without those two
causes. That's all, okay?
If there's no student who's ready to see
them,
and there's no Buddha who prayed to be
seen,
then there won't be any Buddha, okay?
Those two causes have to be there, okay?
They have created the Buddha. Therefore,
the Buddha that you reach by practicing
Mahamudra is also empty.
Got it?
Just I always tell people, even if you
don't understand, just nod.
Okay? Then I'll keep going. Maybe you'll
understand something later.
Uh
Okay.
Then
if you think a Buddha
exists from their own side,
and not from you,
he calls it the biggest mistake you can
make, okay? Right here he says, "That's
the biggest mistake you can make, okay?"
Uh and then right here
the discussion changes.
Okay? And somebody, the person who's
been talking all along, which we thought
was the first Panchen Lama,
says, "So,
for right now
and for the rest of all time,
I will give you up."
Okay? That now it's becomes a
conversation. Someone's talking to
somebody. So far, it's just like a
a teaching about
emptiness, okay? And the and progress
through the path.
And now suddenly says, somebody says,
"If you thought the Buddha you reached
by practicing Mahamudra was real,
then that's the biggest mistake you can
make, and I don't want to make that
mistake anymore. So,
take no offense, but it's time for you
to leave."
Okay? It becomes a conversation at this
moment. It's kind of cool. So,
if we had a real class and if I if I was
examining you tomorrow to let you into
the class,
and I said, "How did it become a debate?
When did it become a debate?" You would
have to say, "Well, he was talking about
Some people never see emptiness in their
whole life, and they don't hear about
it, okay? Are they exposed to it?"
Well, especially when they die. It's
right in front of people, and they don't
recognize it, okay? So, normal people,
you know, they have no idea what you're
talking about when you say emptiness,
but they are
they they're swimming in it as they die.
And they don't recognize it, okay?
Then people are trained, they work, they
work, they meditate, they study, they go
to long room retreats,
and then they translate, and then
they get some breakthrough called path
of seeing. They see emptiness directly,
okay?
And then if they work, work, work, they
become a Buddha. But that Buddha
is coming from people seeds, okay? That
Buddhism comes from. And if you don't
think so, the idea that
the idea that Buddhism not coming from
those seeds is the worst idea you can
have.
So, now the person who's been talking so
far
says, "So, you got to leave my mind."
Okay? Who's you?
The devil, okay? Who's the devil?
Yeah, not understanding that things are
coming from your seeds, basically, okay?
Not understanding that your world is
coming from your seeds. And now the
angel, which is understanding,
says to the devil,
"I know enough now that you should leave
the mind." There's a famous
line in a cowboy movie from the 1940s, I
think. I I tried to find it one day.
And Gary Cooper or somebody says to
somebody else,
"You There ain't room in this town for
both of us."
You know, like, one of us is going to
die
unless you leave, you know? And it's
just like that. So, the angel is telling
the devil, in one person's mind, in one
person's skull, it says, "One of us has
to leave, okay?"
And it's going to be you.
Okay? Understanding says to It's a very
cute argument. It gets very
sophisticated, okay? I counted today
with Renate. I was sitting
I was sitting in the car while she was
doing the beads today.
So, I was just there as policeman in
case the beads got crazy. And uh
I said, "I got to work in the car. I got
to get ready for tonight's thing." Yeah,
okay. What are you going to do in the
car? I said, "I'm going to count how
many wrong meditations the first Panchen
Lama lists in his book so far. How many
s- stupid meditations?" I call them
ineffective meditations, okay?
Ineffective means they look like
meditation, they feel like meditation,
they have some mild effect on you,
but they're not going to help you get
out of
death
and age aging, and they're not going to
help you get free, you know? They are
ineffective. I call them ineffective.
Guess how many so far?
25.
Okay? He In detail, he describes 25
ineffective ways to meditate.
Okay? And uh
then 26 is the correct one.
Okay? Well, sorry.
Not exactly.
We'll get there, okay? Now, I call it
the entrance of an eternal false friend,
okay?
Faux ami.
In French or something like that.
You got to ask Sage.
Uh here we go.
Now, this is This is misunderstanding
talking back to the angel. This is the
devil talking back to the angel, okay?
Uh
Look, as long as this mind has been
here, I've been here.
Okay? And
uh
the person you're trying to kick out is
the person who took care of you all
these years.
I took care of Michael.
All these lifetimes, I took care of
Michael.
I loved you like a father. I loved you
like a mother. I cared for you with
love. I gave you food and clothes, okay?
Who's talking?
The devil.
The devil, okay?
I was the one who brought you to the
ultimate dharma
of wanting things.
Okay? And the other two poisons, you
know?
Uh
I was the one who who wiped from this
mind
any desire to do good karma.
Okay? I'm the one who took care of you,
okay?
And and then wisdom says, you know, I
made her a girl
uh because in in Buddhism we say wisdom
is a left-hand practice, right? Vam
marga.
Uh it's a feminine quality, okay?
Wisdom. So, I made her a girl, I made
him a guy.
I hope that's okay.
Uh
then she says
"Oh, you've been in the mind forever?"
And he says, "Yes." And she says, "But
there is no mind."
Okay? All right. That's where the
conversation goes.
There How could you have been in the
mind? There is no mind. Got it?
Just nod. Okay.
Uh
absolutely speaking what does that mean
in Buddhism? It means without my seeds
from how I treated people in the past,
okay?
Without those seeds from whether I
treated people well or I treated people
bad in the past, without those seeds,
mind doesn't exist. Nothing exists,
okay? Everything's coming from seeds in
my mind, okay?
So actually, who are you to argue with
me
cuz you don't exist either.
Devil don't exist either. And the place
you want to keep the house you want to
stay in called
this mind, this guy's mind, Phil's mind
that doesn't exist either, okay? The guy
who wants the apartment doesn't exist.
And the apartment doesn't exist. What
kind of argument you having with me?
Got it? Just Yeah, yeah, I got it.
Okay. Now
now the devil says, "Oh, yeah?"
"Well, if I don't exist and the mind
doesn't exist, then you don't exist
either."
Okay? He says to the angel, "You don't
exist either.
So, how can you be standing there
arguing with me if I don't exist and the
mind we both want to take possession of?
They both want the same apartment.
Okay? If If the apartment doesn't exist
and I don't exist, then you don't exist
either. Why are you hassling me?
Okay?
Uh
Do And And anyway, who are you to say
nothing happened? You know?
Who are Who are you to say nothing
exists? We all know. Buddha said
causation.
What's that T-shirt, Scott?
Equal.
Cause and effect. Come on.
Your teacher taught that, not me.
Okay?
Of course I exist. I come from cause and
effect. The apartment exists. It comes
from cause and effect. You exist. You
come from cause and effect. What are you
saying I don't exist?
Your teacher said I exist. Independence.
On dependence on causes, dependent
origination. Don't give me this crap
about there's nobody here.
Your teacher said we're here because of
causes.
Okay, got it? This is a pretty cool
devil.
He's quoting Buddhism to the angel. You
know? Don't tell me I don't exist. I
exist in cause and effect. I'm dependent
origination.
Okay?
Your Buddha said that.
Okay? If anyone's going to leave, you
should leave.
Okay?
Uh
Why?
Because And then he calls her Miss
Nothing Exists in an Ultimate Way.
He says, "Miss Nothing Exists in an
Ultimate Way. If anyone leaves, you
should leave because you are denying
that things can exist nominally.
Okay, what do you call that? Relatively.
Okay, what is it What's the other word?
Conventionally, yeah.
Okay, you're the one that should leave.
You're the one who's contradicting the
Buddha.
Because of you're saying that even on a
day-to-day level, nothing exists. Okay?
Then you should get out of here cuz the
Buddha said that's the wrong idea.
Okay, you can't say ignorance doesn't
exist.
I'm I'm cause.
I'm depend I'm dependent origination.
Okay, little miss
exist nothing exists in an ultimate way.
What about all the other stuff that's
not ultimate? What about stuff that
comes from causes, normal stuff? Are you
saying I don't exist? Okay, got it? He's
cool.
He's not a fool. Okay?
Then wisdom says, okay. Now, this is
tricky and this is a big point
uh fight between the two middle way
schools. Okay? Lower middle way says
nothing exists in an ultimate way except
correct
deceptive thing.
Okay?
Except things which have causes.
You know, so
like I don't know.
Uh
you're stopped at the stop light.
Your car goes back.
I'm sorry, the car next to you
goes back.
And
No, the car two cars on either side at
the same moment at a red light, they
back up and you think you're going into
the red light and you're like, "Ah!"
Like that. Okay, it's just relative. You
you you are tricked into thinking
that but it's not true. Your car's not
moving. You don't have to slam on the
brakes, okay? Life is like that, a wrong
reaction to
to relative things. Now,
what if those What if your car really
does slip into the
into the red light? You see, got the
difference?
In the first case, it feels like your
car slipped in the red light,
but it's just relative, okay?
In the second case, your car really did
slip into the red light, okay?
They're both called normal reality,
not ultimate reality. They're both
normal reality, but one is a mistake and
one's not a mistake, okay?
Uh in the lower school, lower middle
way,
they say there's
two kinds of deceptive reality, real and
unreal.
And neither one's real.
Got it? Neither one's ultimate.
But, you know, there's there's normal
perceptions that are correct and there's
normal perceptions that are wrong.
Like your car going into the red light,
okay? Got it?
Anyway,
we'll talk about it.
Uh
And if if
you know,
if according to you my karma isn't
producing the world, okay? Who's
talking?
David.
The angel.
You're always 50% chance to be right, so
just
Okay, and she says to him, you know, if
if if if things don't come from the
seeds in my mind,
then they would have to be unchanging,
okay? I I We were Me and Veronica were
talking about an example.
Uh try to understand, okay?
When I use a pen, okay?
When I write something on her on her
folder, okay?
Ready?
I'm Here, let me just mess it up.
Uh
I'm writing something on her folder.
Yeah, they probably gave me the pen.
Okay, I'm writing something on this
folder, all right? Did the writing come
from the pen?
Even in a relative sense.
That's the question here.
Did the pen make the writing?
Yeah.
No.
You see, lower middle way says yes.
The writing came from the pen, okay?
Higher middle way says what?
My mind is is
images are opening out of karmic seeds
in my mind.
Pen.
Movement. Movement. Writing. Writing,
okay? The pen doesn't make the writing.
The seeds in my mind make the pen.
The seeds in my mind make Geshe
Michael's hand move.
And then the seeds in my mind project
writing.
The writing's not coming from the pen.
The pen came from my mind, the movement
of the hand came from the my mind,
and the writing came from my mind.
Okay? Got it?
So, in the higher middle way, highest
school,
nothing's coming from the pen.
The pen doesn't work.
Okay? The pen doesn't work.
Cool?
In the highest middle way, well, well,
what's the use of that, Geshe La?
You know, if I have to sign a check,
I'll just sign a check. Why do I have to
know that?
Why is it important?
Cuz you can make anything you want
happen at all.
Okay? You can make anything happen
in your life. If If the writing was
coming from the pen, you're stuck.
Okay? If the writing's coming from the
pen, you're stuck. You have no future.
You must die.
Okay? And you must lose everything you
worked for in your whole life, and your
children, and your family, okay? If If
the If the writing's coming from the
pen.
But, if the writing's coming from your
seeds in your mind, then you can change
anything. You could even make cell
phones not ring during the class.
Sorry.
Okay. Okay?
If the writing was coming from the pen,
according to the higher middle way,
it could never change.
Okay? Uh on a practical level,
if the world's not coming from your
seeds
that you plant
by how you treat other people,
then you're then life is finished. You
have no hope. You will all You will get
old. You will die.
And you can't get the things you want in
your life. It's not possible.
Okay? They're not coming from you.
They're just happening. Okay?
All right.
All right. So, then Miss Wisdom says,
"Can Can one thing be hot and cold at
the same time?
Like one uh
We have a tea kettle, right?
It gets too hot.
We bought a new stove.
We bought a gas stove, and the tea
kettle we have is is too hot.
You You can't touch it. You have to use
a uh What do you call it?
Pot holder, yeah.
But at at the moment that that thing is
too hot to touch, okay? Can it also be
too cold to touch?
No.
No, it It's not It can't be all hot and
all cold at the same time, okay?
It It's either hot or it's cold. Hot and
cold
cannot
live together
in the same tea tea pot. It's not
possible. You put the tea pot in the
freezer for a couple of hours,
it'll be cold.
You put it on the stove for 10 minutes,
it'll be too hot to touch. But they
can't be both at the same time.
Okay? Why is he saying that? Why is the
angel uh wrapping up her little section
here in that way?
What's the point she's making?
It's partly coming from you and then not
coming from you at all.
Yeah, but talk about the apartment.
It's not big enough for both.
Yeah.
Okay?
You're hot, I'm cold.
You know,
you can live in this apartment or I can
live in this apartment, but we can't
live in here together. Why?
Because the way you see things and the
way I see things is completely opposite,
you know? You think the writing's coming
from the pen.
I think the writing's coming from my
mind.
It's It can't be both.
It's got to be one or the other, you
know? Okay? So, that's crucial for this
text, okay? You got to understand that
in this text
only one person can get the apartment.
Okay? Either you're going to have wisdom
in your mind or you're going to
misunderstand for the rest of your life.
If If one moves in, the other has to
move out. Okay? And that's what she says
here.
She says, "We are incompatible."
Why? The way you look at the world and
the way I look at the world is just
fundamentally different, okay? You think
the world is atoms bumping into each
other after the Big Bang
and that's what created Trump.
Just random.
Okay? And I think it has something to do
with how we treat people.
That we have to see what we have to see,
okay? Got it? But those two opinions are
They can't both be right. Somebody has
to be wrong.
Somebody has to move out of
here, okay? Got it?
Both of them want the apartment. It's a
fight about a Russian apartment, right?
In Moscow or something. Okay.
Uh
Then he quotes Dharmakirti
who says they are incompatible. Okay.
And it one has to win.
One of them
is looking at something
which could never exist.
Okay, one of them is looking at
something
which could never exist
and the other is looking at something
which is truth.
Got it? What's the thing that can't
exist? What's it called in Tibetan?
Yeah, gaktja. Okay, I don't know why but
people can remember this word.
And sometimes I just use it in a
translation cuz it's
it's such a cool word. Say gaktja.
gak
ja
gaktja
Okay, what's a gaktja?
Writing on Vimala's folder that came
from the pen.
Something which could never exist. How
do they describe gaktja in DCI?
No,
wait, wait, wait. Huh?
Yeah, that's okay but the Buddha
whenever he talked about this, he said
didn't exist in the past
could never exist in the future and it
don't exist now.
Okay, what's that? Writing which came
from the pen.
Couldn't exist in the past, will never
exist in the future and it doesn't exist
right now.
Okay, impossible thing. Okay?
Well, where did the writing come from?
Your mind.
Okay, well, why did it come right after
I put the pen on the paper?
I don't know. You made the comment right
after that.
Okay, got it?
It's not coming from the pen.
It's very important. Okay, Money doesn't
come from working.
Okay? Boyfriends don't come from going
to nightclubs.
There's no connection.
Got it? It's very interesting.
Okay.
Mhm.
Then Shantideva says,
"If you don't understand,
if you cannot identify what's not there,
then you it's hopeless, okay?
If you can't identify what's not there,
it's hopeless, okay?
Uh
Who is that?
I'm not going to do the two husbands
things. You guys know that.
Okay.
To succeed in Buddhism, to get
enlightened,
you have to be able to tell me what's
not there.
Okay? What's emptiness empty of, okay?
And in a simple way, you can say a
boyfriend or girlfriend or husband or
wife who's not coming from you
is is impossible, okay? No such thing.
Okay? Every
irritating person you ever met was a
mirror of you.
That's the bad news. The good news is
you can change them without talking to
them.
Cuz they're coming from here, okay? You
can change your husband.
Change you change the scene. He he will
change. He doesn't have choice.
Okay? If he's not coming from you, then
you should argue and fight and divorce
and
do whatever. Shoot him
in the American way.
Uh
Okay. Mhm.
Okay. Now,
the bad mind, the devil, he's going to
give his answer. Okay, you ready?
Uh listen.
Uh
I've been in staying in this apartment
since it was built. When was it built?
It's Yeah, no beginning. Okay, I've been
staying in this apartment since it was
built, which never had a beginning.
Okay? I've been living here, all right?
Have mercy. Let me stay, you know?
And I'll tell you why.
If you didn't have me in your mind
misunderstanding the writing on Vimal's
folder, you would not have the sense to
take care of yourself.
Okay? You wouldn't go out and get things
and compete with other people. You'd be
starving.
You know, without me?
Okay, now he's drawing a
He's drawing a connection between two
things. What?
Selfishness.
Depends on misunderstanding the pen.
Okay? To think, you know,
that you can compete for money or you
can compete for girlfriends,
you know, to think that
can only happen in a mind which doesn't
understand where things are coming from.
The whole idea of competition and taking
care of myself
before I take care of you
depends on misunderstanding the whole
world. Okay? Why?
What if you do understand where the
world comes from?
You got to think care of other people
first.
Why?
Cuz you want things.
Okay?
The only way to get things
is to give them.
Okay? It's very cool. Okay?
The only way to get anything
is to give it. You see?
But he So, what now listen what he says.
Come on. You don't want me to leave your
leave your mind.
Who's going to
Where's your sense of self-preservation?
You kick me out, who's going to take
care of you? Who's going to watch out
for number one?
Okay? All right, got it?
Just not
This is his argument. Why? Because
misunderstanding the world is the source
of selfishness.
Taking care of number one. Okay? If he
left the apartment, what would happen to
selfishness?
It couldn't exist there. Why?
Because the angel understands to get
something I have to give it.
You see? The The angel understands that.
Okay? The angel has a sense of
self-preservation, but it's an
intelligent sense of sense of
self-preservation, which takes care of
the other person first.
Got it?
But he's making a wrong claim.
What's he saying?
Oh, you kick me out of your mind, you're
in trouble, man.
Who's going to watch out for number one?
Okay? Who's been taking care of you all
these years?
Without me, you would starve.
You people All those people would
outcompete you.
You wouldn't know to take care of
yourself.
You need me.
Okay?
It's kind of cute.
All right.
If you kick me out, hey, you would lose
your oldest friend.
And who's going to come back? Who's
going to want to hang out with you?
Okay?
It's also shameless. What kind of bad
karma you're going to make if you kick
me out of my apartment,
okay?
Then uh
the thing that
the idea that you're going to take over
the apartment and you're going to be the
new wife of our mind
is really bad.
Okay? Okay?
That's a very bad idea, okay?
My lease on this place is permanent.
Okay? Many people have threatened
to kick me out of this mind in the past.
Many lifetimes this guy has tried to
meditate. Always fail.
Okay? He tried so many times to evict
me.
You know, he tried so many times to get
the apartment back. It's just like
Chin-dong's apartment.
Right? How many years you in this
apartment?
Never mind.
They Since she was a teenager, she lived
in the same rent-controlled apartment in
New York. Do you know how hard they've
tried to get her out of there?
It's the same thing. But she's a
Buddhist nun, so it's not going to
happen.
Okay.
He says, "Look,
many people, you know, in the past they
said, 'Oh, I'm going to purify my mind.
I'm going to start thinking right. I'm
going to start practicing Buddhism.'
They all failed.
Okay? He says, 'Why? I gave them my
blessing.'
And I'll tell you something else.
Until you reach the seventh Bodhisattva
level,
I don't even start to move out.
Okay? What's the What happens at the
seventh Bodhisattva level? It was my
pre-Geshay examination debate.
Yeah, you stop seeing the world coming
this way, okay? After you see emptiness
directly,
you understand it's coming this way, but
you don't see it that way. It's still
that's what we call Maya, illusion. It
still looks like it's coming this way,
but you know you're wrong.
You know you're wrong, but you can't
stop. Okay, at the seventh Bodhisattva
level, you can stop.
He says, "Look, even up to seventh
Bodhisattva level, very very high saint,
they still have me in the apartment.
Okay? I'm still there.
Up until the seventh Bodhisattva level.
You're just a normal dude. What hope you
have?
You know? High Bodhisattvas, very high
Bodhisattvas, they I'm still living in
their environment. Okay? What chance do
you have in kicking me out? Come on.
Okay.
Now,
uh
in fact, if you want to know the truth,
it's called the stain.
Okay? Which means
uh the subtle effects on your mind of
ignorance stay in your mind up to the
tenth Bodhisattva level.
Okay? Do you have manifest ignorance?
No.
Are his clothes still in your apartment?
Yeah. Okay, got it? His stuff is still
there.
Like you kicked him out, but his stuff
is still in all the closets.
Seriously, okay? Like the potential
to start thinking wrong again exists all
the way up just just almost to Buddha
hood. Okay? So, you're a normal person?
Are you kidding me? You don't meditate
every day. You get in fights with
everybody. You're so selfish. Woo,
you're going to kick me out?
Are you serious?
I'm
my clothes are still in a tenth level
Bodhisattva's closet.
You know? And you say you're going to
kick me out? Come on. He's He's like, "I
own this place."
Okay? Got it?
Uh
Miss Wisdom, you visit this apartment
very occasionally.
I live here.
Okay, got it?
Got it. Okay.
And by the way,
I brought all my friends to live here,
too.
Okay.
You know people like that. They ask you
can they stay at your house for 10 days.
Two years later, they're still there.
And then suddenly, their three friends
are there, also.
Okay. So, ignorance is like, "By the
way, I'm not the only person living in
your apartment.
I brought my other friends. Who are
they? Refusing to share, jealousy,
deceit, pretending to be someone you're
not, vanity, pride, 62 kinds of wrong
view,
laziness,
refusing to think of others.
We're all here, living here. You know,
it's not just me. My whole family is
here.
Okay? We've been living here for all of
time. You think you're going to kick us
all out?
You know, I'm not alone here. I got like
64,000 friends. 80 84,000 friends.
You are the occasional flash in the pan.
I'm staying here forever as the
confidant of this mind.
If someone of If someone should go, it's
you. Okay? Miss Wisdom.
Okay.
Uh
And then, you made me out to be a demon.
Okay? I'm your younger brother. You like
You put horns on my head. You tell
everybody I'm really bad. Okay?
Then, you're going to kick your younger
brother out?
You know, I come along with you.
Okay?
Then he he makes a very powerful
argument. Okay, ready?
Who put me in this mind in the first
place?
Who put me here?
Karma.
Okay? Karma put me here. And every
Buddhist knows
karma is more powerful than the Buddha.
Okay? The Buddha cannot cancel
karma. Okay? The Buddha cannot say, "Oh,
oh, Kamala, you know, you you kicked the
dog yesterday. It's okay. No no result."
You know, don't worry about it. I I wash
you, you know, and like, don't worry
about it. It's gone.
You know, not even a Buddha can do that.
Then this is very nice argument from
from the devil. He says, "Who put me in
the mind?"
Who put me here in the beginning?
Who put him there?
Karma.
Like, a Buddha cannot cancel karma. You
going to cancel karma?
You know?
I'm here. I signed a contract with the
Buddha to live in this apartment.
Got it?
Okay?
I was put here by karma.
Buddha cannot cancel that contract.
Okay? Don't talk about making me leave.
Karma put me here.
Here.
Uh
Every Buddha of all time working
together trying all the miracles that a
Buddha can do cannot stop 1 minute of
karma.
Okay? You you Even if all the Buddhas in
the world decided to team up against me
and kick me out of this apartment, it's
not going to happen cuz who put me here?
Karma put me here. A Buddha cannot
cancel karma.
Okay? My contract for this apartment is
airtight.
Got it?
All right. And then wisdom says
Pongbu shunne pongbu tso. Say pongbu.
Shunne.
Pongbu.
Tso. Now if you don't know script, you
know,
Tibetan culture well, you you you this
is going to be impossible.
So there's this story about this guy who
had a herd of 50
jackasses.
And he every day he takes them out
to
the pasture
on the mountainside and he feeds them.
He rides around,
you know, and checks on them and
and then
he's come when he comes home he has to
count the 50 to make sure he's got
everybody, okay?
And then one night he's out riding
he gets 49.
He said some snow leopard has eaten my
jackass.
He rode he rode everywhere and couldn't
find number 50.
He's on it.
He's sitting on it.
Okay? You're riding out on the donkey to
look for the donkey you lost.
What's it mean?
The fact that you're here
makes it impossible for you to stay.
The fact that karma signed a contract
with you is why you have to leave.
Don't tell me you're going to stay
forever because you got karma on your
side.
The reason you have to leave is cuz you
got karma on your side. What's it mean?
Karma always runs out.
You know?
That's why people get old.
That's why trees fall down. That's why
nations finish.
Right? Don't tell me you got karma on
your side. If you got karma on your
side, you're out of here.
Got it?
Anything you get by karma is going to be
lost. Okay. Don't tell me karma signed
the contract. If karma signed the
contract, I'm in fat city.
You'll be out of here.
Got it?
What's it got to do with the donkey?
You think I have no right to be here,
but you're riding on the right to be
here. Got it? Cuz you're riding on
karma.
Got it?
Okay. This is just with you, okay?
And then she says, "You want to know
who's really been in this apartment
forever?
It's wisdom.
Because emptiness has been in this mind
forever.
The cap-
the cap- the cap- capacity
for freedom has been living in this mind
since it was designed.
Okay? You can't make a mind
without putting in the capacity for
freedom.
It's part of every mind.
Mahamudra.
The emptiness of this mind is the key to
the liberation of this mind.
You want to talk about who's been here
forever?
I've been here forever.
Why? Because this mind itself is flowing
out of seeds
from the past deeds of this person.
Therefore, there's no part of this mind
that came from nowhere.
Therefore, this mind is nirvanable.
Got it?
Okay?
Don't tell me you've been here forever.
I've been here longer.
Okay? When they built this mind, they
put the key inside.
Okay, got it?
Just none.
But, okay, last three lines here.
Okay, that primordial Buddha,
the Buddha that was put into you from
the factory
when you were built.
Okay? That's been there all along, but
it's veiled by things that are not
innate. They can be removed.
Okay? The veils can be removed. Okay?
The nature of a human being is pure.
The nature of the human mind is beauty.
Okay?
And it's
veiled.
And it will be
The veil will be removed, and you will
see what a human mind is. I'm the one
who's been here forever.
The human mind is angelic.
It's its nature.
It came out of the factory that way.
There's parts of the mind which are not
built in, which came later, and they
they've made a curtain.
And we tear away the curtain, and you'll
see the angel
that this person has always been.
It's called the primordial Buddha. Okay?
Cool.
She's got a cool argument.
If anybody's ruining our happy home,
it's you.
If anyone put double horns on your head,
it was you.
As long as I live here, you're going to
be homeless.
And I don't care.
She's Now, those of you who are
interested,
uh Tenzin Tenzin Pema Kundrol Tsal,
Tenzin Pema Kundrol Tsal. Okay? There's
an ancient custom in Tibet that started
with the
Padmasambhava.
Okay? The first Buddhist lama, big lama
to come to Tibet.
He brought a dagger, a a holy dagger.
You've seen these ritual daggers, you
know.
And they're it's called It's called a
tenpo.
That that dagger is called a purpo.
Uh ritual dagger.
And when he came to Tibet,
he he knelt on the ground and he
and he he drove the dagger into the dirt
and he said, "This belongs to the
angels.
This land belongs to angels, you know."
He staked it out.
You know.
So, those of you who are translating,
this is a tough
It means you have no right to stake your
claim here.
Who's talking to who?
Yeah, the angel says to the devil, "You
put your dagger back in your pocket cuz
you don't own this place.
Okay? We claimed this place already.
What? The human heart is ours.
Okay? You've got no right here.
It's not in your place. You go someplace
else. The human heart is mine.
Okay? Very beautiful.
Okay.
Now,
okay, here's where you guys get in
trouble.
But if you still say you want to put
your dagger here,
just listen to some logic I have
about
where the world comes from, okay? Just
listen to a few things I have to say
about where the world comes from.
And I think you will tear your own house
down.
Okay? Got it?
So, you're in trouble now. Why?
The first Panchen Lama is about to
present 25 wrong meditations and he's
going to sh- present them and and blow
them up
one by one. The rest of the 100 pages,
okay, is all the kinds of stupid
meditations you can get sucked into.
And then one by one, he will explode
them.
Okay, so this is a long list
of
Uh you know, I was going to translate it
as wrong meditations, but it feels like
judgmental, you know, I don't want to
say someone's meditation is wrong.
I'd like to call it ineffectual.
Ineffective meditations, okay?
They won't get you anywhere. You will
you will do them and you will die and
you will go to hell.
Uh frankly, I don't say that in a DCI
talk, but this is an ACI talk.
In this little room, I can say what I
want to say, okay?
Waste your life on a meditation that
doesn't free you,
you're in trouble, okay? You're in
trouble.
All right? It's like drinking poison or
something, okay? So, he's going to have
before he gives you the right one, okay?
So, as we go through these 25,
uh
Why why does Why does he teach it this
way?
Because every one of us is attracted to
one of those 25.
Me, too.
Every one of us would be attracted
to some of them, okay? So, in Buddhism,
there's this way of teaching where
you list all the mistakes one by one.
And then finally, you hit one that says,
"Wait, Geshe la. That one sounds good to
me."
Yeah, well, that's your problem.
Okay? So, we're going to go through 25
uh different kinds of meditation
that
they're just a waste of your life and
you will die.
And you will never know what happened.
Okay? You will just
get old and die, okay? Doing this stupid
medi- not stupid, but it didn't work.
I call it selling fire extinguishers
that don't work.
And you don't know till you have a fire
and you push the button and nothing
happens.
What's the fire?
The week you're dying. The week you're
dying and then you're like pull out pull
out this meditation you've been doing
for 10 years. Oops, it doesn't work.
Okay.
Oops.
And it's too late then. You
I get at least one letter a week from
people who used to be my student saying
help me.
I got cancer or or or something I I I
swear I get a letter every week.
And it's help me. I I got one
Jiggy which is not here.
I got one from a a lady in Phoenix. She
says I I got it last week. My mother's
dying. Help me.
Teach me teach me all you know about
death and death meditation. I've been
teaching it for two years at Dying
Mountain. You didn't come.
You And you want me to write you an
email?
You know
You know what I mean?
And I inevitably I get this and it it's
frustrating, you know.
So anyway, stop coveting. All right.
You can search from the top of your head
to the soles of your feet.
You'll never find out if you are
the sum of all your parts put together.
Okay.
You won't find
anything.
Let me make it simple, okay? Cuz many
lamas teach this in a ridiculous wrong
way.
And it doesn't make any sense. And you
Someone told me a Chinese guy told me,
"When you go to China, say confusing
stuff. People will respect you more."
You know, I'm like, "No, but it's not
confusing. They're confused."
The teachers are confused, okay? Are you
the sum of your parts? No.
Okay? Is Geshe Michael Does my body
equal my legs plus my arm plus my head
plus my
torso? Is that Geshe Michael's body, all
those things together?
First of all, let's do simple. Is my
foot Geshe Michael's body?
No, that's easy. We don't have to talk
about it.
The hard thing is,
is my two legs and my two arms and my
head
and my torso, is that all together, is
that Geshe Michael?
Buddhism says, "No." Okay? Why?
One part's missing. One part's always
missing.
What's the last part?
The seeds in your mind.
The seeds in your mind, okay? People
have Alzheimer's,
they they forget who their kids are.
Their kids come to visit them and
they're like,
"Who are you?"
Okay? It means the kid is not the kid
cuz they can't think of the kid as the
kid anymore. When you can think of this
body as Michael's body, then it becomes
Michael's body.
Why do you think of Michael's body as
Michael's body? Karma forces you to.
Okay? Karma forces you to. Why?
Because you served the sick in the past.
And that put a seed in your mind to see
a human body.
Okay? That's how you got your human
body. You served sick people in the
past. Okay, got it?
If you didn't serve sick people in the
past,
and you had these two arms and two legs
and a head and a body, you wouldn't see
it as a body.
Okay? You wouldn't don't a human body.
You only see it as a human body cuz you
serve the sick, okay? Stop serving the
sick,
you will lose this body. Okay?
Coming from you.
That's the final part. So, are you your
arms and legs and and middle and head?
Yes or no?
Are you individually? Is my foot Geshe
Michael?
Body?
No. Is all of Geshe Michael's body parts
together Geshe Michael?
No, there's one part left.
The karma to see it as Geshe Michael.
Got it?
That's an easy Okay, so forget all the
other explanations you heard, they're
all wrong. And they feel wrong
cuz they are.
Okay? You are not your parts.
You are in the void.
I'm going to kick you in the ass part
with my leg part.
How do you think about that?
Okay, never mind. I shouldn't say bad
words.
Somebody's going to yell at me at home
later on.
Uh
okay, that part's easy.
It's the same with your mind, okay? It's
the same with your mind. Take all your
emotions,
take all of your knowledge, take all of
your mistakes,
they don't equal Michael's mind, okay?
Until
I have helped depressed people or I have
helped people with emotional
trouble, okay?
And and if I have,
I will experience the parts of my mind
as a mind. And if And if that wears out,
I will get Alzheimer's.
Got it? Okay? Got it?
Are you all the parts of your mind
together? Are you all your emotions and
memories together?
Is your mind
Is Michael's mind the sum
of his memories, emotions, etc.?
Yes or no?
No, there's one part waiting. What?
He has to think of his mind as his mind.
Well, what unifies all the parts of his
mind into his mind?
Serving other people who have mental
problems.
She told me I shouldn't stick my tongue
out like that. I'm sorry.
She says, "Sometimes when you make a
point you go
I said, "I didn't I wasn't aware of
that, but now I am."
Okay.
So, it applies to your body, it applies
to your mind. Okay?
You are not the sum of your parts
until you have the final part
which is helping someone else.
The karma of having helped someone else.
Okay?
Uh 5 more minutes we'll take a
break.
Now, once you understand that this is
angel talking. If you understand that
thing about the part, the illusion is
torn. The root of the mind is ripped
down. The poison tree is falling down.
Okay? And the evil one is in his grave.
Okay?
Okay? The one who thinks you can have a
body and mind without taking care of
other people.
He's We just buried him.
Okay? Who's him?
The devil. Yeah.
Misunderstanding. Okay?
Uh
And then she goes on and she calls it
sexy stuff, but it doesn't matter. You
know what it is.
Okay.
And then she calls it the single song.
What's it mean?
Anyone want to want to take a shot?
Eka rasa.
Single song.
Yeah, but what's the point?
Why single?
Yeah. Everything's like that. Body,
mind, car, house,
wife,
dog, nose,
left eye, right eye.
Okay? It all singing the same song.
What?
You got to be nice to other people or
you cannot have me.
Okay? I'm coming from those things.
Okay? Don't
Don't think I'm not coming from
anything. I am.
Okay? And they're all singing the same
song. We come from your good stuff.
Every object in this room is singing the
same song. Okay? But you can't hear it.
It's called one song, right? Ekam
Advityam
in Sanskrit, one song.
Then here she gets really poetic and
that's okay. You don't need that.
And now now she makes a point and then
I'll stop for a break. Okay? We'll stop
for a 10-minute break, which will
stretch into 15 and I'll go late.
Uh
She says, "You have a choice in your
life. Okay?
You can examine your life.
You can question where things are coming
from. You can ask if there's a better
way to run the world. Okay? You can be
curious.
And you can try to
make a breakthrough about where the
whole world is coming from. Or
you can just leave it.
Okay? Just live your life.
You know? Eat.
Sleep. Work.
You know? Raise kids.
Die. Lose your house. Kids die.
You can do that. You have a choice. You
can not question where everything's
coming from.
And and then okay, everything's fine.
There's no contradictions.
You know? The I wrote a letter with my
pen.
Okay, leave it.
That's okay. That's one approach to
life. Don't question all this stuff.
Don't go deeper.
Just live your life, you know? And and
you will go through the same cycles as
everyone. You will
be young and and strong and then you'll
get middle aged and slightly stupid. And
then you'll get old age like me and
John.
And you'll be more stupid and then you
die.
You have a choice, she says. Wisdom
says, you always have a choice. You
know,
if you don't question who put the
writing on her folder,
life is okay, it's easy, it's normal.
But it's deadly.
Okay?
Or you can question.
And that's a hard road to follow, but
it's the road to get free.
Okay? It's the road to
to get to get out of this world. This
kind of world, okay?
All right.
We're not even halfway through the
review.
This is going to This is why it's taking
70 years.
Okay, last thing then we'll take a
break.
Wisdom's been She's The angel's been
saying everything's empty. Why?
Because there's nothing you can point to
which is not coming from your karma.
That's the meaning of emptiness. You
know, sometimes I tell people show me
your finger, point to something in this
room that's not coming from you.
And then a real Buddhist will go like
That's Then you arrive at emptiness. Try
to find a thing in this world room
that's not coming from how you treat
other people.
And there's nothing. That's the meaning
of emptiness, okay? Now, she says,
"Did you just learn emptiness?" Yes.
What is Tell me again what is it? It's
that nothing in this room is not coming
from how I treat other people. Is that
the meaning of emptiness? Yes.
Who taught you that? You did, Geshe
Michael.
Who made Geshe Michael?
You know, I like to tell DCI audiences,
if you don't like what I'm saying,
that's your problem.
You created me. If you like what I say,
that came from me.
Okay, but really nothing comes from me,
okay? So, at this point,
the angel says a very sweet thing.
She says, "By the way, Mr. Devil,
my side of the conversation
is coming from
you."
Okay? I'm an echo in a canyon. She calls
herself the echo in the canyon.
You know, yell down in the canyon, you
get something back. She says, "You don't
like me? You made me."
You know, you don't like wisdom in your
mind? You made me. You planted me. You
put me here, okay?
I also have emptiness.
The angel also has emptiness.
Meaning, she didn't come here randomly.
She came here from someone's karma.
Whose?
The devil.
If you don't like me, that's your fault.
Okay, let's take a break. If you don't
like the food at the break,
that's your fault. Okay, please come
back in 15 minutes and let's do some
questions and answers, okay? Okay, you
guys have an extra microphone?
Sweet. Uh, any questions for 15 minutes
and then I have to go home.
And we'll continue tomorrow. We didn't
finish the review, which is why we
always get behind.
Who had a question?
Geshe la talks too much.
Hello.
Hi.
Um I have a question
regarding karma and seeds in relation to
the
recent uh
Las Vegas shootings that happened, where
some people got shot and some people
didn't, some people live and some people
didn't.
And it seems, I was talking to Nicole
about this the other night, but it seems
in that moment that things are so random
in a situation like that,
but then it was presented to me that
well, it's not random, it's all those
people had karma or seeds for that
situation. And I'm
just kind of
Yeah, it's mind-boggling.
wrapping
Yeah.
So, that was just something recent that
I've been kind of
meditating on.
There's a There's
a a classic answer.
And uh
it's hard. The answer is hard, but the
answer goes like this.
Uh and this is Shantideva. This is 1,300
years ago.
He said, "Well, there's three
possibilities. Number one, it's just
random.
Uh
just who gets shot, who doesn't get
shot, whether or not someone's shooting
tonight or not, you know, is completely
random.
That's the first possibility. There's no
sense to it.
Uh second possibility,
uh there's a divine being. There's
someone in charge of the world, and they
choose who gets shot and who doesn't get
shot.
Uh
and and we can't figure out their
decisions,
you know? And you know, if you're going
to create a being and then kill them,
well, why not just do it
painlessly? If you If there's something
wrong with the being you created,
just, you know,
cancel them. Uh like, that's the second
possibility. The third possibility is
that
there's a complete logic to everything,
and you only get what you deserve.
Uh and it's not 50%.
It's either 100 or it's zero. So, either
things are random,
and everyone gets something they don't
deserve,
or they get exactly what they deserve.
Then you get into the question of
well, it didn't seem like some of those
people killed anybody, or
they weren't shooting at people, and and
and then it's a the the answer
is a combination
of uh
a discussion of watermelons
and a discussion of uh
I don't know. Uh democracy. Okay, you
can say that. What's the watermelons
mean?
It means there's a
consistency of cause and effect. You You
cannot
I just We just grew our first
watermelons, right, this year. I got
like seven watermelons.
Uh I was so proud of myself. Like, Pacha
did whole forest, but I just did seven
watermelons.
And uh you know, I felt really proud of
myself.
But what the way it works is you take a
seed out of a watermelon, and you plant
it, and with certainty, you know you're
not going to get a banana.
You know, there's some kind of weird
What's going on, I don't really know.
But if I take a seed out of this fruit,
and I plant it, I will get that fruit.
So,
in the third view of the world,
violence cannot be begotten except by
violence.
Those people must have done something
violent before. That's the theory.
That's just the theory that everyone
deserves what they get, good or bad, and
there's no exceptions.
Uh
Then the second question is, well, well,
this person didn't do anything like that
in their past. I've known them since
they were a kid. They were nice people,
you know, and then there's comes in the
I call it democracy, but um
this whole federal bureaucracy right
now. I heard the number today.
I don't know if it's like $3 trillion.
It's like a a quarter of the people in
this country work for the federal
government.
And I pay for it. She V knows I argue
about it a lot. I'm paying for them, you
know. And uh
It started with an idea in Benjamin
Franklin's mind as he walked up the
steps in Philadelphia in 1774.
Those $3 trillion and
50 million employees were a random
thought in his thought in his mind as he
walked up the steps to the rented little
apartment in 1774.
What Why am I talking about that? A
small
tiny
passing thought can create a country
that lasts for 300 years. You see? And
and according to Buddhism
a small violence done to someone can
escalate into into a killing.
You know, and and those are the two
factors here. A
According to a Buddhist answer number
one, no one ever gets anything they
don't deserve. Number two
they might have done a tiny thing that
that grew like You know, and I I some
guy I was in I was in Taiwan, I think.
And some guy raised his hand, he says,
"I don't accept that."
JB, raise your hand. I don't accept
that.
Then I went like this.
I said, wait, let's talk about your arm.
He said, what? He's like trying to get
his arm back. I'm like, give me your
arm. He's like, no, no. I said, wait.
You say it's not possible, right? He
says, right, it's not possible. I say,
how many cells
made this arm?
This This arm, I checked on Google.
That's all you have to say for authority
anymore.
I checked on Google.
It's a hundred trillion cells in the arm
that you're using to alert me that you
don't agree.
How many cells did it come from?
Two.
End of story.
Go home.
End of story. Your mom gave one cell.
Your dad gave one cell.
This hundred thousand cells
has survived for 70 years.
69.
OKAY? SO, DON'T RAISE THIS HAND AND tell
me it's not possible cuz your hand
proves that it is.
You see what I mean? And he's like,
Okay, your arm proves The arm that you
raised to say it's not possible proves
that it is possible. You are riding on a
donkey looking for a donkey.
Now, see uh
Those are the two Buddhist answers. Now,
if you're giving a DCI program in
in
We're going to Denver next month, right?
For the Young Presidents' Association,
you don't talk like that. You don't say
that. You say it's a terrible thing.
Things happen.
You know, obviously people there didn't
deserve it.
We should try to limit guns in this
country. You know,
that's why Buddha gave four different
schools
depending on the audience. So, for a
level one audience,
Buddha would say, "Oh, of course they
didn't deserve it." And
and it's just some crazy guy and, you
know, probably
and it's true, we all have some
responsibility
for creating this person. You see what I
mean? Like that would be a better way to
go.
You know,
or someone asks you about the Holocaust,
you don't talk like that, you know? Or
why did I lose my baby or something like
that? You don't
you don't give the detail.
But frankly, that's what it is.
Yeah.
Any more questions?
Yeah, and I wish it wasn't like that,
but but maybe
if we deserve everything we get, we
would just work harder at deserving good
things.
Okay, one more question.
So, so basically, we have a question
from the live stream.
Okay, cool.
So, this comes from Alejandro in in
Mexico. And he asked about
earlier on in the talk, you talked about
that there could only be one tenant in
the apartment. And later on, you talked
about they're both living there kind of
like
at the same time or like brothers. And
he wanted to ask about the clarity of
that. What What happened in the
argument? Cuz it originally you said
they could only one be living there, but
then
it turned out that the the devil is
living there, but but the angels have
always
always been there.
The devil referred to himself as her
little brother.
And he said, "Don't put horns on your
little brother." So, it seems to imply
that they were in the same family at
some point.
And she's painting him black,
you know, and he's objecting.
And
no,
the fact is they cannot coexist and they
never lived in the apartment at the same
time. And they're they're not
They're related in some ways. They both
have emptiness. They both have their own
causes.
But no, they can't coexist. Um
But but I'll I'll give this to
Alejandro.
Think about this. The The main point
when you say they can't live in the same
apartment
is that
the way they see things is incompatible.
It's not physical presence or or
something like that. You see what I
mean?
The point isn't that
where they are.
The point is
uh either
like you have an argument with someone.
Someone hurts you.
Someone calls you a bad name.
And then at that point, at that moment,
like I get called bad names on the
internet.
So at that moment, I have a decision. I
can
I can believe that it's coming from
someone else.
Or I can believe that it's coming from
me because I judge people all the time.
You see what I mean? Like I have a
choice.
But
but the the choices are incompatible.
You must go one way or the other. You
must either say
you know, these are bad people attacking
Yeshe Michael or
you have to say this is coming from the
habit I have of judging people I meet.
But you can't have it both ways.
It's that that's the main
meaning of incompatibility here. That's
why they can't live in the same
apartment. One mind
at the same time, okay? Cuz they can
come in and out real fast.
You know, you can be a Buddhist for like
20 minutes and then then you get pissed
off.
You know,
but in one moment it's impossible for
one human mind at 800007
to both think
that this person criticizing me in the
internet is coming from me
and at the same time to think they're
not coming from me.
And that's that those two guys can't
live in the same apartment. Now,
can they
you know, can the one thought run out 10
seconds later and the other thought
moves in for 10 seconds and yeah, that's
the story of any Buddhist's life.
We are schizophrenic.
You know, we're like really nice people
for 10 minutes and then we lose it for
10 minutes. These often ask me, you
know, well, well, doesn't your own
philosophy say blah blah blah and I'm
like, yeah, but that's not the point.
Yeah.
Okay, we're going to stop there.
Uh, I I planned to stop at I made it 68
rather than 79 cuz I thought people
might have things to do. People might
have to get back to Phoenix and stuff
like that. So,
we'll continue tomorrow. We'll continue
the review tomorrow. I'll try to go
faster so we hit some new stuff but
but I I
I have never gone back through we've had
10 sessions like this in the last 7
years. I've never gone back and tried to
see the whole flow.
And I almost feel like if we can see the
flow together, it it's not so important
that we get to the 24th meditation. If
we
if we understand
why 23 are wrong
then then we can make a solemn promise
to get together more often here since we
have a play
that John and Connie built and I'd like
to thank them for that.
Let's let's use the place more often and
and you know, I'm used to talking to a
thousand or two thousand people and uh
but this is actually quite sweet for me
also cuz cuz it's close friends and
and it's kind of less pressure and I can
actually see your face in the last row.
And uh
it's kind of nice. So, okay?
So, we'll try to do do it more often.